<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A looking-glass for the wise and foolish, the godly &amp; ungodly Wherein they may see, how much it concerns them to be wise unto salvation, before it be too late. By John Ryther, minister of the gospel in Wapping, near London.</title>
            <author>Ryther, John, 1634?-1681.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 58 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58034</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2440</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222745</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833883</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833883</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38361</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58034)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38361)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2215:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A looking-glass for the wise and foolish, the godly &amp; ungodly Wherein they may see, how much it concerns them to be wise unto salvation, before it be too late. By John Ryther, minister of the gospel in Wapping, near London.</title>
                  <author>Ryther, John, 1634?-1681.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 100 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J.D. for Henry White, at the three Bibles in the Minories,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Copy tightly bound; with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Congregational Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Repentance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38361:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38361:1"/>
            <p>A LOOKING-GLASS FOR THE WISE and FOOLISH, THE GODLY &amp; UNGODLY.</p>
            <p>Wherein They may ſee, how much it Concerns them to be Wiſe unto Salvation, before it be too late.</p>
            <p>By JOHN RYTHER, Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>Wapping,</hi> near <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 9.10.</hi>
               </bibl> The fear of the Lord is the beginning of Wiſdom, and the knowledg of the Holy is under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 12.23.</hi>
               </bibl> But the heart of Fools proclaimeth fooliſhneſs.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. D.</hi> for <hi>Henry White,</hi> at the three Bibles in the <hi>Minories,</hi> 1677.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:38361:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38361:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Deſign of the Author, by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting thee with this littie Piece, is no other than caſting in his Mite, with many other abler Hands, towards making thee Wiſe to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which indeed is <hi>The Wiſdom, The true Wiſdom,</hi> and will make thee one of Wiſdom's Children, in ſuch an Age, wherein ſo much folly and mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs appears, eſpecially in reference to Mens greateſt Concerns, <hi>viz.</hi> The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of Eternity, and a future World.</p>
            <p>This true heavenly Spiritual Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, will be thy greateſt intereſt, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and dying; therefore it is high time to look about thee, whether thou art a wiſe, or a fooliſh Virgin; whether thou haſt got this true Oyl into thy Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel and Lamp, left thou, for all thou haſt trimmed thy Lamp, ſhouldſt he ſhut
<pb facs="tcp:38361:3"/>out from going in with Chriſt, to the Supper of the Lamb. Didſt thou never read that word in all thy life? <hi>Who is a wiſe Man, and endued with knowledg among you? Let him ſhew out of a good Converſation his works, with meekneſs of wiſdom,</hi> Jam. <hi>3.13.</hi> (So ſay I) O ſhew thy wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom! make it appear, render it viſible to all Spectators, in that thou art ſo far from making a mock of Sin, that thou darſt not meddle with it at any rate; that thou abhor'ſt it as Hell, that thou flieſt from it as from a Serpent that thou doſt hate it as a Toad; this ſhews thy wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom thou ſeeſt before thee, thou conſiderſt Actions, and the conſequences of Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and doeſt act like a rational Man; What will this ſinful Courſe of mine, end in? Is it not a diſcovery of Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like folly, to play with a Rattle-Snake, and take it up in our hands, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it hath a ſhining skin, and looks with a ſplendid outſide; or to ſwallow a Pill of Poyſon, becauſe it is pleaſant
<pb facs="tcp:38361:3"/>and guilded? Or to venture on Rats<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane, becauſe it is ſweet? Such folly, ſuch madneſs is this, in poor Sinners, in thouſands of poor Souls, that play with ſin, put it into their Boſoms, nay, keep it as a ſweet morſel under their Tongues, becauſe it pleaſes and flatters for the preſent. It was good Counſel of the Philoſopher, <hi>Look upon Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures going, and not upon them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> O, poor Sinners, how doth want of Heavenly Wiſdom (which much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in fore ſight) carry many a ſoul vailed and mufled to Hell! O therefore, when thou readſt this Piece (let me beg of thee) conſider as well as read; read, read leiſurely, and make not too much haſte over good Ground: This is the fault of moſt Readers, they do not mind their ſtops. As thou readeſt, take Pauſes, and ask Queſtions, Is not this ſo? O, my ſoul! Is not this true? O my Conſcience! Canſt thou evade it, or deny it? Is not this the Truth that muſt Judge thee another day? Another
<pb facs="tcp:38361:4"/>Requeſt I have to thee (Read belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly) If thou believeſt not, why doſt thou read? Will it not be loſt time, and is there not too much of that precious Sand run already out of thy Glaſs? O, how hard it is to bring Sinners to believe, before they feel! Thou that wilt not believe, ſo much Folly is bund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led up in thy heart, now ere long, will lament thy infidelity and thy folly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, when it will be paſt hope. Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, let me ask thee this Queſtion: Haſt thou not been fool enough already, but thou muſt hold on to be ſo, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever God, Conſcience, Miniſtry, Word, or Rod ſay? O, hear that good Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel be-times, and practiſe it. <hi>The fear of the Lord, is the beginning of Wiſdom. And a good underſtanding have all they, that do hereafter.</hi> Begin to be wiſe then, before it be too late, and God ſay, He will put no more pieces, ſuch pieces, into the hands of ſuch Fools. Conſider, conſider, poor ſouls, you have but a little time to get
<pb facs="tcp:38361:4"/>Wiſdom in, a little time to get the true Oyl; your Glaſs is running faſt, and often meets with an Inviſible hand to ſhake it too; nay, you cannot tell what ſudden ſtop this frail Glaſs of your Lives, may meet with. O there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, will you yet loyter? Will you? dare you ſtand idle any longer, that have loſt ſo much time? That have done ſo little work? and yet have had ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pieces in your hands? But like ſo many poor, ſtupid, fooliſh ones, had not hearts to make uſe of the ſame. Do you never ask your own hearts the Queſtion, Is there any Wiſdom in the Grave, any Work in the Grave, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you go? Is not this life your only Market for this Commodity? O, that Sinners did but think the Grave too dark a Shop, to do any Soul-work in, they would not certainly leave ſo much work undone, when they come to die! Ah, Sinners, when will you be wiſe? Do not you know, either now or never, for Heavenly Wiſdom? Remember the
<pb facs="tcp:38361:5"/>fooliſh Virgins, when they crîed, <hi>Lord, open, open unto us,</hi> came a day after the Fair: Now the door was ſhut, and it was too late. <hi>I</hi> have one other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt to thee (good Reader) Either read (as one reſolved to Practiſe) or lay down, and never read at all: what will thy reading elſe be, but one day a great Aggravation, both of thy ſins and Condemnation? What, to read and never the wiſer? To read and never the better? What, to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of Folly, and never labour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Wiſdom? To go on in thy Folly, while thou knoweſt thou doeſt ſo? O, how ſad is this! If thou ſhalt grow a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wiſer for Heaven, by thy reading the Piece now put into thy hand, the Auther hath both his Deſire and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and begs thy Prayers that it may be a Bleſſing ſtill to thee, and others, in the Hand of God.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine, In the Service of the Goſpel,</hi> J. R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38361:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 14.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Fools make a mock, at Sin.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="part">
               <p>SInner, or Believer (for one of theſe thou art, that takes up this little Piece to Read) I will propound a Queſtion to thee, and beg thee in bowels to thy Soul, to propound it to thy ſelf, and preſs thy Heart to return a direct Anſwer; the Queſtion is but ſhort, but yet of great weight and worth. O my Soul, what am I? Is it not an eaſie Queſtion to ask? How ſoon may thou put this to thy own Soul? But, O how hard is it to Anſwer! Am I a Fool, or a Wiſe-man? Am
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38361:6"/>I wiſe to Salvation? Am I a fooliſh Virgin, or a wiſe? Canſt thou not Anſwer it? Look ſeriouſly into the enſuing Treatiſe, and thou mayeſt meet with ſomething that will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute towards a Solution of the preſent Queſtion.</p>
               <q>Fools make a mock at Sin.</q>
               <p>The Text is a very brief, yet full Deſcription of all ungodly Perſons; who they are, <hi>They are fools.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. We have the Perſons deſcribed, <hi>They are fools.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. We have the Practice, <hi>They make a mock at Sin.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">I. Their Perſons, <hi>They are fools.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. They may think themſelves Wiſe; they may be wiſe in their own Conceit, but they are nevertheleſs Fools. <hi>Seeſt thou a man wiſe in his own conceit? There is more hope of a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38361:6"/>fool than of him,</hi> Prov. 26.12.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They may be wiſe in other mens Conceits, and be cried up for Wiſe Men in the World, yet Fools in Gods account. Their Poſterity approve their ſayings, they are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten down in other Mens Kalenders for Wiſe Men, but what ſays God? How are they written down in Gods Kalender? <hi>This their way is their folly,</hi> Pſal. 49.13.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Probably theſe Men may be wiſe for the World. <hi>The Children of the World are wiſer than the Children of Light in their Generations,</hi> yet they are Fools. <hi>He that getteth Riches, and not by right, he leaveth them in the midſt of his days, and at his end ſhall be a Fool,</hi> Jer. 17.11. He is a Fool for Eternity, though a Wiſe Man for this preſent World.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Theſe Men may be wiſe to do evil, and yet the greater Fools. <hi>For my People is fooliſh, they have not known me; they are ſottiſh Children,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38361:7"/>they have no underſtanding, they are wiſe to do evil,</hi> Jer. 4.22.</p>
               <p>There are two words in the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> for a Fool, and they are both given to ungodly Men in Scripture, <hi>[Nabal]</hi> Fooliſh, or Evil, ſuch a Fool as hath his underſtanding fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and depraved, whereupon he becomes vile and wicked. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther word for a Fool is <hi>[Moreh]</hi> which ſignifies one Rebellious. <hi>If a man have a ſtubborn and rebellious Son,</hi> &amp;c. Deut. 21.18. there we have the word: Such an one is a Fool, it ſignifies (as<note n="*" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Anſw.</hi> from this comes the Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> one obſerves) one that changeth and turneth to the worſe, yea, in Heart and Action, and in particular turneth from, and oppoſeth the Word of God. It ſeems Fool and Rebels are the ſame with God.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:38361:7"/>II. We have the deſcription of their Practice in the Text, <hi>they make a mock at Sin.</hi> Thus is their Folly made manifeſt. Thus they proclaim their Folly, they make a mock and ſcorn of that which is the Object of Gods wrath and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, they ſport themſelves with it: <hi>Fools ſport themſelves in doing miſchief. It is a ſport to a fool to do miſchief: But a Man of underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hath wiſdom,</hi> Prov. 10.23. O what Fools are theſe, to mock at that which caſt the Angels out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>Adam</hi> out of Paradiſe, which brought Chriſt an Errand from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to Earth, and which, without Repentance, will ſend them on an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand from Earth to Hell. And what, Sinner, make a mock at Sin? thou mayſt as well make a mock of God, of Chriſt, of Heaven, of Hell, of Damnation: And art thou ſo hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that thou canſt find in thy heart to laugh in the face of all theſe?
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38361:8"/>What, Sinner, not one ſpark of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, nor Religion left thee? At what a rate haſt thou ſinned, that canſt make a mock at Sin? Such an one as thou, art in the higheſt form of the Devils ſchool: Thou <hi>ſitteſt in the ſeat of the ſcornful,</hi> Pſal. 1.1. Or, in the <hi>chair of Peſtilence,</hi> as the <hi>Septu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agint</hi> reads it.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 1. Then ungodly ones (or Sinners) are Fools in Gods ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, in Scripture account, which is Gods Kalender.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 2. To mock at Sin is the greateſt diſcovery of Folly in the World: <hi>Fools make a mock at Sin.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Firſt, That ungodly Sinners are Fools. You may ſee God calls them ſo every where in Scripture where they are mentioned. Prov. 1.7. <hi>The fear of the Lord is the beginning of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:38361:8"/>Wiſdom, but Fools deſpiſe Wiſdom,</hi> and Inſtruction. There are natural Fools, who are defective in princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Reaſon; but it is meant of Spiritual Fools, or Fools in a Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſenſe, who are defective in prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Religion. The whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Apoſtate Children of <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> are called a <hi>fooliſh, and unwiſe Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> Deut. 32.6. Sin is called <hi>mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>folly,</hi> Eccleſ. 7.25. The <hi>wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs of folly,</hi> even of <hi>fooliſhneſs and madneſs,</hi> 2 Chap. 12. It is not only folly, but madneſs. When God brought the poor Prodigal home, he is ſaid firſt to come to himſelf, he had play'd the fool and the madman before, to leave ſuch a Fathers houſe. Nay, the higheſt Acts of Sin, are called Folly in Scripture. As that act of <hi>Shechem</hi> defiling <hi>Dinah,</hi> it is called <hi>working folly in Iſrael,</hi> Gen. 34.7. and that act of <hi>Amnon</hi> to <hi>Thamar,</hi> 1 Sam. 13.12, 13. <hi>Thou wilt be as one of the fools in Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:38361:9"/>
               <p>But we ſhall now demonſtrate to the ſinner, what a fool, what an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant fool, an ungodly Man is, be he who he will.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Is not he a fool that neither fears, nor foreſees evil and danger; when they are faſt approaching? Doth not Wiſdom conſiſt in fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight? Are not the <hi>wiſe Mans eyes in his head, while the fool walks in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> Eccleſ. 2.4. <hi>viz.</hi> He acts rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally and judiciouſly, while the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, the fool, walks on without ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fear or wit. <hi>The prudent Man</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>foreſees evil.</hi> Oh, ſays he, yonder is a Storm, I muſt prepare for it; this is Wiſdom, and he hides himſelf: <hi>But the ſinner goes on,</hi> blunders on, <hi>and is puniſhed,</hi> Prov. 22.3. He blunders on, until he blunder himſelf into Hell at laſt, by taking no warning. He conſiders not, ſees not his danger, therefore fears not. He ſees no Wrath, nor Hell, nor Damnation, to lie before
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38361:9"/>him: He doth not foreſee, therefore he doth not fear. He doth not fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee his miſcarrying to all Eternity, he doth not foreſee that if he goes on, he is loſt for ever; therefore he doth not foreſee it: But now a wiſe Man foreſees it will be thus, and therefore he ſets himſelf to work out his Salvation with fear and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Is not he a Fool that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands not his way? <hi>The wiſdom of the Prudent, is to underſtand his way: But the folly of Fools is deceit,</hi> Prov. 9.13. They think they underſtand their ways, and think they are right, their ways are right in their own eyes: But alas! they deceive their own Souls, they walk in darkneſs, and know not whither they go; they think they are going to Heaven, and alas, poor fools, they are going to Hell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In their folly they go rſtray,</hi> Prov. 5. ult. O poor ſinners, that are
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38361:10"/>walking into Hell, are not you fools? What could you ſay, if an Angel ſhould meet you, and ask you this queſtion, Whither go you, poor ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners? What art thou bound to Hell? What meaneſt thou to run ſo faſt? Wilt not thou be there ſoon enough? Take up ſinner, take up: Why doſt thou thus ſpur on? What couldſt thou anſwer to ſuch Queſtions, thou poor fooliſh ſinner. If thou be right, why doth Wiſdom cry after thee to turn thee? <hi>Ho, every one that is ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, turn in hither,</hi> Prov. 1.22. O, how doth Wiſdom ſee poor Souls travelling in the Broad-way, like Fools going to the Stocks, and crys after them, <hi>How long will ye ſimple ones love ſimplicity?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Is not he a Fool that takes no care to prevent afterclaps of Danger? Wiſdom conſiſts in fore-ſight and in prevention: <hi>Is it not the property of a fool to ſay, I had not thought, my ſins would have brought me to this?</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:38361:10"/>Doth not the Lord in his Word, and in his Rod, cry out to poor ſinners, (as <hi>Jonathan</hi> ſaid to <hi>David</hi>) <hi>As the Lord liveth, there is but a ſtep betwixt thee and death?</hi> Oh! ſays God, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, ſinners, there are but a few ſteps betwixt you and death; a few Years, Months, it may be Days, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt you and Hell, betwixt you and Ruine; and yet ſuch Fools are poor ſinners, that they are not ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citous to prevent their miſery. Oh, how it will cut poor ſinners to the Heart another day, to ſign out that doleſul note, We had not thought the Great God was in good earneſt with us. We had not thought Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Threatnings would have proved ſuch Realities! O this will be the Worm that will ſo wofully torment them! We were told of all this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-hand, and might have preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it. O then they will cry out, what Fools they have been: But all too late, they ſee their folly by the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38361:11"/>light of that fire that ſo intollerably torments them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Is not he a Fool that doth not conſult the end of his way? The end in all wiſe Agents is firſt in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, though the laſt in Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Here is the difference betwixt Wiſdom and Folly: The one ſays, What will this end in? As the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle argues in that caſe, <hi>What fruit had you in thoſe things whereof you are now aſhamed? For the end of thoſe things is death,</hi> Rom. 6.21. But now a Soul that is not wiſe for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and Salvation, may ſay, What will this Way, this Courſe, end in? Will not this be bitterneſs in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end? Will it not be Wrath, eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Death, Damnation, in the end? <hi>This is a way that ſeems right to a man:</hi> But what is the end of it? <hi>The end of it is Death,</hi> Prov. 14.12. Ah Sinner, Sinner! Art not thou a fool that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver looks before thee? Waſt thou wiſe, would'ſt thou not look before
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38361:11"/>thou leapſt? Why doſt not thou ask thy ſoul, O my ſoul, what will this ſin of mine end in? Whether will this Courſe and Way of mine at laſt lead me? Is not ſin the Devils high way to Hell? And doth not this Courſe lead down to the Chambers of Death? Ah, poor fool? All wiſe Men that have their Eyes in their Heads, pity thee, they ſee whether thou art going; and thou wilt ſee too when it is too late.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Is not he a Fool that cannot tell how to make a good choice? Wiſdom you know is much ſeen in choice. The trial of a Fool hath ſometimes been made thus. Fools and Ideots are not to inherit Lands; and when they come to try them, they lay down Apples, and Gold, and if they chuſe the Apples before the Gold, they are concluded Ideots. Oh, doth not God put this to trial, ſinners, fooliſh ſinners! Here is Gold and Apples laid before you, Creature-Comforts,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38361:12"/>the Accommodations of this Life: What are theſe but ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Apples (as <hi>Joſephus</hi> tells of) that grow about the Lake of <hi>Sodom,</hi> that look bravely to the Eye, but as ſoon as touched, they crumble to duſt? And do not many thouſand poor fooliſh Sinners, chooſe theſe before the Gold? Before the Gold tried in the Fire <hi>(viz.)</hi> Real Grace. Such as make ſuch a choice are fools, and ſhall never Inherit. Did not <hi>Moſes</hi> tell the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he laid <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> before them, (<hi>Deut.</hi> 30.19.) and put them to their choice? And Oh! what folly ſinners is it, to chooſe Death ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than Life. Oh! this will be the ſting of thy eternal miſery, that thou like a fooliſh wretch, didſt make ſuch a choice; it was thy own choice; thou art undone for ever, but it was thy own doing: Thou thy ſelf art the cauſe of all this. This will juſtifie God in thy own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38361:12"/>to all Eternity: Oh, what cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out is there (Sinner) in Hell! What a fool was I to make ſuch a choice! I might have been happy for ever as I am now miſerable, if I had made a wiſe choice.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Is not he a Fool that is afflicted day by day, and ſtill goes on and keeps his courſe of ſinning ſtill. <hi>A reproof enters more into a wiſe Man, than an hundred ſtripes into a Fool,</hi> Prov. 17.10. A Fool will be a fool ſtill, give him one blow after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther until you tell an hundred. O how many blows have many ſinners had! Sometimes a blow in their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, another while a blow in their Bodies; another while a blow in their Families; ſometimes in their Trading; nay, added to all theſe, ſometimes in their Souls, by Convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions under Ordinances. And thus God lays on time after time: But what comes of all theſe blows? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las the poor ſinner is a fool ſtill; he
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:38361:13"/>goes on ſtill. <hi>Bray a fool in a Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter among Wheat with a Peſtle, yet will not his fooliſhneſs depart from him,</hi> Prov. 27.22. Theſe Fools are worſe than Mad-men and Bedlams, they are often reſtored to Reaſon again by Correction and Severity. Poor ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, haſt not thou been ſuch a fool? O how many blows haſt thou laid under! How many Rods hath God ſpent upon thee? How often hath God made thee ſick by ſmiting thee? And yet Gods Rod hath not whipt out the bundle of Folly that is wrapt up in thine Heart. As thou haſt been, ſo thou art a poor fooliſh one to this day. O poor ſinner! what if upon thy incorrigibleneſs, the Lord ſhould ſay to thee, as he did to them, <hi>Why ſhould you be ſmitten any more? You rebel more and more.</hi> O how ſad would this be! Sinners, did you never read that word, <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.29. <hi>Judgments are prepared for the ſcorners, and ſtripes for the backs of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:38361:13"/>Fools.</hi> Thou art both, whilſt thou makeſt a mock at ſin: It is no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if the Lord have Rods for ſuch backs.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Is not he a Fool who hath a price put into his hand, and hath no heart to uſe it? <hi>Wherefore is there a price in the hand of a fool to get Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſeeing he hath no heart to it,</hi> Prov. 17.16. Ah ſinners! how many opportunities have you had in your day to get Wiſdom for your Souls, for Heaven and Eternity, and you have let them ſlip? O what grand folly is this, to play the fool for your precious ſouls! Is this to redeem your time? Is this to walk as wiſe ones? As thoſe that are wiſe to Salvation? Is he a wiſe Mariner amongſt you, that when the Wind preſents, will ſtay on the <hi>Downs,</hi> or drinking a ſhore, and ſo looſe his Voyage? Is he a wiſe Man, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant in your repute, that doth not eſteem his Seaſons to buy his Goods
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:38361:14"/>and Commodities at the beſt hand? Is he a wiſe Husbandman that doth not obſerve his Seaſons, for getting his Seed into the Earth? And this is the caſe of poor fooliſh ſinners; the motions of the Spirit preſents the Gales of Grace, comes about in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, the Commodities for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World, may be had at the beſt hand? Seed for Heaven may be ſown, and yet all theſe Prices ſinners have no heart to make uſe of. Ah poor ſinner! Are you not like <hi>Ephraim, ſilly Doves without an heart?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. Is not he a Fool that neglects the doing of that now, which he never ſhall have opportunity to do hereafter. Now ſinner is your Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, your Goſpel-Summer, your Harveſt for your Souls. <hi>And is not he a wiſe Son that gathereth in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, but he that ſleepeth in Harveſt, is a Son that cauſeth ſhame,</hi> Prov. 10.5.</p>
               <p>O, how many Summer-Seaſons
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:38361:14"/>of Grace have you had, and yet what little Winter ſtores have you laid in? What little ſtore of Grace, what little ſtore of Experience, what lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſtore of Goſpel-Promiſes; and is not this wiſdom in Summer, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for an approaching Winter? <hi>There are four things</hi> (ſays <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>that are little, but exceeding wiſe; the</hi> Ants <hi>they prepare their Meat in Summer, the</hi> Conies <hi>they make their Houſes in the Rocks, they provide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt danger: The</hi> Locuſts <hi>they go out in Bands, they provide againſt the aſſault of an Enemy, and ſo go out to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. The</hi> Spider <hi>taketh hold with her hands and is in Kings Palaces, ſhe fortifies her ſelf againſt danger,</hi> Pro. 30.24, 25, 26. They are all, we ſee provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Creatures, they provide in their preſent time againſt time to come. Ah poor ſinners, you cannot do your work hereafter! Now is your day to work in, there is no work in the Grave whither you go. Either now
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:38361:15"/>or never is the cry of Ordinances, the cry of Preachers, the cry of the motions of the Spirit of God; And will you ſtill be ſuch Fools, as not apply your ſelves to your preſent work? Is it not great folly to looſe ſuch opportunities, as you ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have the like? Ah ſinners! tell me, tell your own hearts, would you be ſuch fools in other things? And is it nothing to play the ſool with your precious ſouls, with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Seaſons of Grace? Come ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, ere long you will be of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mind, either here or hereafter; either when you die, or are dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Is not he a Fool that for ſhort and momentary Pleaſure, will part with eternal and everlaſting Joys? Was not that Cardinal a Fool as wiſe as he thought himſelf? Who ſaid, he had rather looſe his part in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, than in <hi>Paris.</hi> We read of ſome that fancied a kind of Eternity
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:38361:15"/>to themſelves here in their enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and what-ſays God of them, Pſal. 49.11, 13. <hi>Their Poſterity ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove their ſayings, but this their way is their folly. Their inward thought was, their Houſes ſhould continue for ever,</hi> &amp;c. Ah ſinners! Is not this egregious folly and madneſs, for a meſs of Pottage to ſell an heavenly Birth-right? For an intereſt in Earth to let go Heaven? For Paper and Packthred to let go the Commodities themſelves? The Commodities of Eternity, for the faſhions of this World that paſſeth away? Alas poor Souls! Are not your ſinful pleaſures ſhort-liv'd? Nay, when they are gone, do they not leave a ſting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them? Was it not good Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of the Philoſopher, Look upon Pleaſures going, and not coming. What are they but like the crackling of Thorns under a Pot, make a blaze to warm for the preſent, and are gone. And for ſuch things as theſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:38361:16"/>to looſe an eternal Inheritance that fadeth not away, O what folly and madneſs is this.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Is not he a Fool, that repents when it is too late. O what folly is this! Wiſdom appears in prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing repentance: Ah what a fool was <hi>Eſau,</hi> when he had ſold his Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.34, 38. <hi>He then came in, and cried with a great and bitter cry, yea, an exceeding bitter cry, and loud unto his Father, bleſs me, even me alſo, O my Father. And</hi> Eſau <hi>ſaid, haſt thou but one Bleſſing Father? And he lift up his voice and wept.</hi> But alas, all this was too late, it was out of due ſeaſon: Therefore we have the Author to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> telling us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.17. <hi>That when he would have inberited the Bleſſing, he was rejected; for he found no place of repentance, though he ſought it care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully with Tears.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh the folly of the afterwards Repentance! The fooliſh Virgins it
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:38361:16"/>is ſaid alſo came afterwards; their Repenting was too late, the door was ſhut; they pray now; they cry now; they knock now; they repent now; but alas! all is now too late. Ah fooliſh ſinners, you ſhould have done it ſooner! Hell is full of repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance but it's inſignificant repentance, it will never alter their eſtates: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider now theſe ten Demonſtrations, and ſinners, you may by them know whether you be fools, or no. Fools in Gods account, or no; fools for Heaven, or no. O ſinner, wilt thou be in good earneſt one half hour, now in all thy life, now that thou haſt read over theſe things, wilt thou promiſe me before I go any further? Wilt thou be ſo kind to thy ſoul, as to think them over? To ask the Queſtion again and again? O my ſoul, art thou ſuch a fool as now thou haſt heard of, as now thou haſt read of? Be in ſober ſadneſs with thy own heart, and ſee thy face in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:38361:17"/>this Glaſs, that thou mayſt know thy ſtate. Now ſinners, if your Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be a little concerned, I would then have you apply things home to your own Conſciences.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Application.</head>
                  <p>Let us then improve it, learn we hence. If the ungodly Man be the Fool in Gods account. O what dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is their betwixt Gods reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Mans. God doth not judg as Man judgeth; Men and Women are not what they are in Mens looks, but what they are in Gods. He is not commended, who is commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of Men, but whom the Lord commendeth. Men ſay ſo and ſo but what ſays the Scripture? <hi>This i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the Voice of God.</hi> You may think your ſelves to be ſomething, and you may be nothing, (<hi>Gal.</hi> 6.3.) and others may think you to be ſome thing, and yet you may be nothing
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:38361:17"/>yea, worſe than nothing. O what a poor empty thing is it to take up in a name, to live with others, and yet be dead. To be counted a Wiſe Man, a Sober Man with others, and be accounted by God for fools. O what ſatisfaction can there be in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wiſe for Earth, and yet be fools for Heaven. He is only a wiſe Man that paſſeth ſo with God now, and will paſs ſo with him at the great Day: Thou mayſt go with Men now, with Miniſters now, yea, with Churches now, and yet not go with God then. O how current do ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Souls go now with Men, that I am afraid will be found counterfeit Coyn at the great diſcovering Day: O then, never take up in the reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and judgment of Men, as to thy Eternal ſtate.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Then learn we hence, where true Wiſdom conſiſts. O how much are the Sons of the Earth miſtaken! Men may be well for the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:38361:18"/>World, may have deep Heads for the compaſſing the things of this preſent Life, and yet be fools for their precious Souls: The Rich Man in the Goſpel was ſo, for all his projects: <hi>Thou fool, this night ſhall thy ſoul be taken away.</hi> Men may be wiſe Men for great Gifts and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and yet fools for their ſouls. <hi>Thou haſt hid theſe things from the Wiſe and Prudent, and revealed them unto Babes,</hi> Mat. 11.25. Alas, this Wiſdom was Fooliſhneſs to the <hi>Greeks,</hi> which were the great Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of their day, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. <hi>Where is the Wiſe? Where is the Scribe? Where is the Diſputer of this World? Hath not God made fooliſh the wiſdom of this World?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here it will be inquired, in what particulars then doth true Wiſdom conſiſt? wherein lies this true Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Wiſdom?</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Is not this true Spiritual Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to provide for ones Eternal well
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:38361:18"/>being? And is not he a wiſe Man that is wiſe unto Salvation? <hi>And that thou from a child</hi> (ſays <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy</hi>) <hi>haſt known the holy Scriptures, which are able to make thee wiſe unto Salvation,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.15. Now, this is the only Wiſdom that comes from above; nay, this Wiſdom alſo leads the Soul thither again. Canſt thou be wiſe, and never ſecure the intereſt of thy precious Soul? Is this thy wiſdom to neglect thy Eternal Concerns? Thou wouldſt be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a fool to neglect the concerns of thy Family, of thy Trading, of thy Ship, of thy Shop. And are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of Eternity of greater moment? Sinners, can you think it your wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to cumber your ſelves about many things, while you live in a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal neglect of the one thing neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? Would any think him a wiſe Man, that did eagerly purſue Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers blown up in the Air, while he neglects his Shop and Trading in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:38361:19"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:38361:19"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:38361:20"/>the World? Would that Merchant be accounted a wiſe Man, that while he ſhould be at the Exchange, ſhould amongſt a company of Boys, be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing a Kite blown up in the Air? And yet this is the caſe. Ah ſinners, your Spiritual Wiſdom lies in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit of your beſt intereſt.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Is not he a wiſe Man, that doth that which he came into the World for? This is great Heavenly Wiſdom. Poor ſinners, do you e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver conſider for what ends you came into the World? Was it to follow your luſts? Was it to take your ſwinge in ſin? Was it to be ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up of your ſenſual pleaſures? Was it to gratifie the wills of the fleſh Did God give you immortal ſouls to purſue ſuch ſenſual employments Sure ſinners, God had other deſign in ſending you into the World; thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> was your errand thither to ſue ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> your pardon, to get an intereſt i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Chriſt, to get your peace made u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:38361:20"/>with God: Do you ever think of theſe things, poor Souls! This is to be wiſe for another World.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Is not he a wiſe Man that doth his proper work in its ſeaſon? Wiſe Men will not only be found work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but they will be found employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their proper work. <hi>Bleſſed is the Servant whom his Maſter ſhall find ſo doing</hi> (viz.) <hi>doing his proper work.</hi> It is a great piece of Chriſtian Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to find out, and fall upon ones proper work. The wiſe Servant will be found doing what his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter hath peculiarly ſet him about; is it humbling our ſouls for ſome particular guilt? Is it getting power againſt ſin? Is it getting the ſence of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Pardon of ſin ſealed up to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ul? Is it laying in more Grace for a Rainy day? O to be doing this york is great wiſdom! This is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er work, and further this muſt be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>one in its ſeaſon too; this work <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſt be done while it is to day. <hi>Work
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:38361:21"/>while it is to day,</hi> &amp;c. Herein is wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to obſerve Times and Seaſons for ſuch works, the neglect of which occaſioned God to complain of his own People, <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.7. <hi>Yea, the Stork in the Heavens knoweth her ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed times, and the Turtle, and the Crane, and the Swallow; but my People knoweth not the Judgment of the Lord.</hi> All theſe Creatures have a natural inſtinct, to know their times and ſeaſons. So in this caſe, there is much wiſdom. O ſinners, what a ſad thing will it be, when God ſhall ſay unto you upon your Death-beds, when you cry to him for Mercy, and Pardon. O, you ſhould have done this in time! in its proper ſeaſon, while you had health and opportunities, calls and motions of the Spirit of Grace upon your hearts. But now it is paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, I will not hear you; Prayer is now out of ſeaſon, and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance out of ſeaſon. O now it is
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:38361:21"/>baſt time! O how will this cut the ſoul! Will not this be bitter? Will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t not reach to the heart?</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Is not he a wiſe Man that gets his work done for Eternity, while he hath means, and helps, to further him? O ſays the wiſe Man, it may be I ſhall never enjoy the like means and opportunities. It may be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in all my days, ſit under the like Miniſterial Showres again, it nay be never be under the like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reathings of the Spirit. O there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſays the ſoul, I will hoyſe ſail, will no longer ſit ſtill, but up and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e doing. Ah poor ſinners! Can my of you tell how long your day of Grace may laſt? Have you any leaſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f your Goſpel-Liberties, any more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an of your Lives? Can you tell but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>our Sun may be darkned once more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t Noon-d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y? And if your Light hould be on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e more put out, would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>our work go on well in the dark? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nner, ſinner, wilt thou never be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:38361:22"/>brought to debate theſe matters of Concernment ſoberly with thy ſelf?</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Is not this wiſdom to get that done, which if you let alone un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, your ſouls are undone for ever? O, ſay wiſe Men for the World, this muſt we do. Why, what is the matter there is a <hi>muſt</hi> upon it? Elſe we are undone, our Wives and Children undone. Well, and there is ſomething that muſt be done, or elſe your ſouls are undone; and this is the dreadful undoing of all. Thou mayſt be undone (as thou call'ſt it) as to thy Eſtate, as to thy Trade, and may recover it again; many have been ſo. But when thy ſoul is undone, thou art for ever undone.</p>
                  <p>You will, it may be, ask what is this undoing?</p>
                  <p>It is to be loſt for ever. To be damned. To be puniſhed with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting deſtruction from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord, and the glory of his Power. Alas! what mourning
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:38361:22"/>is there over loſt Ships, ſometimes amongſt you? over loſt Relations? over loſt Eſtates? But what are theſe to the loſs of ſouls? The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer are recoverable loſſes, but the latter is an irrecoverable loſs. And O, what wiſe Man will hazard ſuch a loſs? If your Ventures at Sea be conſiderable, you will be ſolicitous to enſure. O poor ſinner! your Ventures are very great, and it will be your great wiſdom to enſure; and know you this for your comfort, the Enſurer ſhall never fail, nor break.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Is it not wiſdom to be doing that which you have been doing ſo long, and is not yet done? O, ſays a wiſe Man, I have been often about ſuch a Buſineſs and Concernment, and one thing or other doth put me off, and I have neglected and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed it, but I will no longer defer it. O, Wiſdom will ſay thus for the ſoul, Have not you been often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:38361:23"/>ſolving to break off your ſin, often thinking you would turn from the evil of your ways? Saying with the Prodigal, <hi>I will ariſe and go to my Father.</hi> But O ſinner, is it not yet to do? Have you to this day been as good as your word? O poor ſouls! what if Death ſhould clap an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt upon you, before you get it done? Have you any leaſe of your Lives? May not you be ſought for in the Morning, and not be found? Is it not then wiſdom to put off that no longer which you have put off too long already?</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Is it not wiſdom to do that now, which is impoſſible to be done afterwards? A wiſe Man will not hang a Buſineſs of Concernment up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may-be's and uncertainties? O no! Thus will a wiſe Man argue, It is certain it may now be done, but it is certain it cannot be done af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, if it be not done now. There is no wiſdom nor work in the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:38361:23"/>Grave. He that dies a fool, ſhall be damned for a fool. He will have more wiſdom in Hell, or however he will there ſee his folly, but he muſt bear it, and the merit of it to all Eternity. Now is the day of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; and wiſe Men (I have told you) take Time by the fore-lock, they redeem it: It cannot be done afterwards. O, how poſitive is God in the caſe! <hi>Luke</hi> 13.25, 26. <hi>When once the Maſter of the Houſe is riſen up and hath ſhut to the Door, and you begin to ſtand without and to knock at the Door,</hi> &amp;c. But what was the anſwer? <hi>Depart from me, I know you not whence you are.</hi> Yet they plead priviledges: <hi>We have eaten and drunk in thy preſene, and thou haſt Taught in our ſtreets.</hi> O, they would not be ſaid nay! but doth Chriſt call his firſt words in again? O no! <hi>I tell you, I know you not, depart from me: Be gone you wretched and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſouls, be gone.</hi> O cutting words!
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:38361:24"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:38361:24"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:38361:25"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:38361:25"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:38361:26"/>Were theſe wiſe Souls or Fools, judg you?</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Is it not wiſdom to do that, which we have but a little time to do it in? Were you to live the age of <hi>Methuſalem,</hi> or the age of the Patriarchs before the Flood, you then might have ſomething to ſay for your folly, in delaying the great work of your ſou's. But alas, what is your Age before God? <hi>David</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers the caſe, <hi>Thou haſt made my days as an handbreadth, and mine age is as nothing before thee,</hi> Pſal. 39.4, 5. Suppoſe, ſinners, that you ſhould live threeſcore Years and ten, a full Age: what is this? You have an hundred Years work to do in this time; and what is a days time to a weeks work? Or a weeks time for a years work? This is the caſe, poor ſinners. Time is ſhort. And is not he a fooliſh Traveller, that hath a Journey that is large to go, and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Winter day to do it in, and yet
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:38361:26"/>he will have it Noon ere he ſet out? In ſhort days, you ſay, it is now Noon, and now Night. Alas, poor ſinners! It is not only Noon with many of you, and the Sun of your Life may ſet at Noon-day, but at four a Clock, or five of the Clock, in ſome of your days of Grace? And is it not wiſdom to make haſte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it be night, a night of utter Darkneſs, eternal Darkneſs with you? O ſinners, ſpur on, put on, and mend your pace, elſe you will be nighted.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Is it not wiſdom to do that now, which will bring great returns of wiſdom when you die, when you come to your Journeys end? Wiſe Men will be doing that for the preſent, which will turn to good account, though they ſee not good of it for the preſent. So a wiſe ſoul for Eternity, for Heaven, this ſoul will be doing that which will bring great returns. Wiſe Merchants,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:38361:27"/>and wiſe Mariners, ſtudy to make good returns. Here come your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns, you wiſe Chriſtians, when you come to die, O then, the ſoul will have returns of Peace and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. This was the return that <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah</hi> had: <hi>Lord, remember me, how I have walked before thee with an upright and a perfect heart.</hi> O that is a ſweet word of <hi>Peters: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the rather, Brethren, give diligence to make your Calling and Election ſure. For ſo an entrance ſhall be miniſtred unto you abundantly, unto the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting kingdom of our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.10, 11. Is it not greatly your wiſdom to make this ſure, to have Peace, Joy, and Comfort, upon a Death-bed at laſt.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Is it not wiſdom to do that now, which you ſhall not have to do afterwards? Now thou art mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, breathed upon, convinced, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined, and haſt a good will to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:38361:27"/>and to return from the evil of thy ways: O do it ſpeedily, for it may be, neglect this time, and thy Heart may be hardened. <hi>Jezebel</hi> had ſpace given her to repent in, but ſhe repented not. Alas poor ſinner! it may be thou wilt be judicially hardned, inſtead of mourning, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting, or believing afterwards. Now if thou put theſe together, and compare them with the other ten in the Doctrinal part, I think ſinners, you may eaſily ſee who is the Fool, and who is the Wiſe Man, and which of theſe you belong unto. Come ſinners, rouze up your ſelves, if you have plaid the fool thus long, for the Lords ſake, for your ſouls ſake, for Chriſt's ſake, let me beg of you, let me prevail with you, that you play the Fools no longer; leſt, as you have lived, you ſhall die, leſt you die Fools. And let me tell you, ſinners, there is no fool like the dying fool, for the dying fool will be the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned fool.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:38361:28"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 14.9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <q>Fools make a mock at Sin.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>WE have done with the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the Perſons in my Text, the ungodly Man, the Fool. We are now come to the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of his Practice, <hi>He makes a mock at Sin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What he is, you have heard; but now we muſt enquire what he doth. The Text tells us, <hi>He makes a mock at Sin.</hi> He is not only a Fool, but he manifeſts his folly; according to that word, <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.16. <hi>A fool lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth open his folly.</hi> Or, <hi>ſpreadeth his folly, layeth open the dung of his own fooliſhneſs.</hi> (Some read it) <hi>The ſhame of his folly ſhall be ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad,</hi> (one reads it) <hi>The heart of fools proclaimeth fooliſhneſs,</hi> Prov. 12.23.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:38361:28"/>
               <p>Wherein doth this diſcovery of this folly conſiſt? The Text tells us, <hi>They make a mock at Sin.</hi> Some think the ſenſe of it to be this,<note n="*" place="margin">Thus ſome car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it.</note> 
                  <hi>They make a ſport of it. Seek not to appeaſe the wrath of God kindled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them for it, but amongſt the Righteous there is favour:</hi> (viz.) <hi>Among them the favour of God, when they have offended, is ſought for by all means; and being ſought for, by mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is obtained.</hi> Others thus, Fools not finding the Scourge of Sin, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Puniſhment of it, not tied to the Act of it, as if they were mockt, when they are told of the Puniſhment of it to come, they make a mock at it, and go on in their wickedneſs. The favour therefore the Righteous ſhews them, is quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to let them feel the Rod of Juſtice; while they puniſh the offence, they ſhew great love to the Offender.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:38361:29"/>(Some read it,<note place="margin">Arias Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus in loc.</note>) <hi>[Stul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum quiſque palliabat delictum.]</hi> Every Fool will hide his fault. And O what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is this! The favour therefore that the Righteous ſhew him, is to let him ſee his ſin. I think it is a good reading, <hi>They make a mock of ſin,</hi> (viz.) A ſmall matter, a light mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of it, a matter of Laughter and Merriment, Sport and Recreation. O what an height of ſin, what a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of impudency are ſuch ſinners arrived at! Mocking at that upon Earth, that ſouls are mourning for, &amp; ever in everlaſting burnings! what ſinners, mock at that now, that you muſt mourn over here, or hereafter, to all Eternity? What, make a Jeſt of that which is matter of Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Is going to Eternal Flames, ſinners, a jeſting buſineſs? Ah poor ſinner, thou ſhalt aſſuredly have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of mocking at ſin, when God ſhall mock at thee, as thou once
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:38361:29"/>mockt at ſin. Stay here, ſinner, read no further, unleſs reſolved thou wilt conſider the next words thou readſt. If all this while thou haſt not laid one word to heart, canſt thou read it without fear and amazement? <hi>I will alſo laugh at your Calamity, and mock when your fear comes; when your fear comes as deſolation, and your deſtruction cometh as a whirl-wind: When diſtreſs and anguiſh cometh upon you, Pro.</hi> 1.26, 27. The meaning of it, is, ſinners ſhall be ſo tormented in their own Conſciences,<note place="margin">Ridere Dei eſt nolle hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manae Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctioni miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere, <hi>ſays one.</hi>
                  </note> their ſin and guilt laying hold upon them, as if God mockt and laught at their torment. This laughing of God, is, that he will not have pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty upon humane Affliction.</p>
               <p>The Obſervation I would inſiſt on, is this:</p>
               <q>To make a mock of ſin, is the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt diſcovery of Folly in the World.</q>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:38361:30"/>
               <p>We muſt inquire, Firſt, What is meant by ſuch as are mockers at ſin.</p>
               <p>Secondly, We muſt inquire into the Pleas that lead ſinners into this great piece of Folly.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, We muſt inquire into the Reaſons, why it is ſuch great folly, <hi>To make a mock at ſin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, We muſt Improve it, by way of Application.</p>
               <p n="1">1. What is meant, or who are meant by ſuch as are mockers at ſin?</p>
               <p n="1">1. Sometimes this Mocking is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for Deceiving: as ſhe ſaid to <hi>Samſon,</hi> Judges 16.10. <hi>Thou baſt mocked me, and told me lies, deceived me.</hi> So poor ſinners, they deceive themſelves, while they mock at ſin. Obſerve how my Text comes, <hi>In the folly of fools is their deceit.</hi> They deceive themſelves, while they make a mock at ſin. Ah ſinner, whilſt thou art mocking at ſin, doſt thou know what thou art doing? Art thou not deceiving thy own ſoul?</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:38361:30"/>2. Sometimes it is taken to Jeſt, or Sport, even to Deriſion, (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.13.) either by Words, or Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture. Thus they make a mock at ſin, making a ſport of it: that is made a deriding matter with ſinners which is a damning matter with God: God takes notice of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of Perſons in ſuch caſes. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom do you ſport your ſelves? Againſt whom make ye a wide mouth, and draw out the tongue?</hi> Iſa. 57.4. Theſe are actions of ſcorn, and God takes Cognizance of them: The Lord ſees you, ſinners, when any of you make a mock at Him, or his Word, Ways, or Servants. This in the General.</p>
               <p n="1">1. By making a mock at ſin, is underſtood a ſlighting, and deriding at the Threatnings of God; uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they that make a mock at ſin, make a mock at the approaching Judgments of God. Thus <hi>Lots</hi> Sons in Law did, he was to them as one
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:38361:31"/>that mocked. Thus did the <hi>Jews</hi> in <hi>Ezekiel</hi>'s days, when they took a ſcornful Taunt, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 12.27. <hi>The Viſion is prolonged, the Viſion is prolonged; the Viſion that he ſeeth, is for many days to come.</hi> Tuſh, ſay poor ſinners, this is far enough off; as thoſe Scoffers did in <hi>Peters</hi> time, <hi>Where are the promiſes of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</hi> So ſay theſe, Where are his Threatnings, are they not long a coming? As thoſe did, who ſaid, <hi>It is not near, let us build Houſes, this City is the Chaldron, and we are the Fleſh,</hi> Ezek. 11.3. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> had Propheſied about thirty Years before of the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> beſieging the City, as you may ſee. <hi>What ſeeſt thou</hi> Jeremiah? I <hi>ſee a ſeeth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Pot, and the face thereof was to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the North.</hi> Here was that now they ſpake of: Now, ſay they, the old Prophet is miſtaken, is this a likely thing, that after thirty Years, ſuch a ſtrong City as <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſhould be
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:38361:31"/>the Chaldron, the ſeething Pot? They ſpeak of it by way of a ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Irony, but yet it came upon them. Ah, ſinners, you may mock at that which hangs over your heads, and is ready to come down upon you.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Before ſinners arrive at this height of ſin, they mock at the Meſſengers of the Goſpel; there is this to be underſtood in making a mock at ſin. We read of ſuch as mocked the Meſſengers of God ſent amongſt them, until the wrath of God broke out againſt them, that there was no remedy: O now, it is no wonder if they make a mock at ſin, ſeeing they mock at thoſe that are ſent to denounce Divine Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings againſt ſin.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There are ſuch as make a mock <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t the People of God: Thus many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id at <hi>David, He was a deriſion to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hem, he was the Drunkards ſong.</hi> We read of ſuch as <hi>ſit in the ſeat of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:38361:32"/>the ſcornful.</hi> 1. Some of theſe mock at the ſufferings of the People of God, which is no ſmall degree of ſin, that ſay, <hi>Aha, aha, ſo would we have it.</hi> You know what God ſaid to the Poſterity of <hi>Eſau,</hi> Obad. 12.13. <hi>Thou ſhouldſt not have looked on in the day of my Peoples Calamity, neither ſhouldſt thou have ſpoken proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the day of his diſtreſs,</hi> &amp;c. O what a ſad ſtory was that, of the People of God, <hi>Lam.</hi> 2.15, 16. <hi>All that paſs by, clap their hands at thee, they hiſs and wag their heads at the Daughter of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>ſaying, Is this the City that Men call the Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Beauty, the Joy of the whole Earth? This is the day we have looked for, we have found, we have ſeen it.</hi> Now, this is a great height of ſin, to mock at Gods Peoples ſufferings and ſorrows. 2. Many mock at their Duties and Services, at their very Prayers, and this is alſo a great height of ſin.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:38361:32"/>4. By making a mock at ſin, is underſtood ſuch as make a mock at the Ways of God, at the whole Cauſe of Religion: Such as ſcoff at Holineſs, there are many ſuch in the World, that mock at Prayer, at Hearing, at the ſtrictneſs of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, at the Ordinances of God, yea, make a mock at Repentance for ſin.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Inquiry,</hi> What are the leading Occaſions to this Folly, of making a mock at ſin? They pretend ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for it, this is their folly, but they have ſome pretended Reaſons for this their wicked practice.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Occaſion of this ſin being long before it be diſcovered, it lying long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id, occaſions ſinners to make a mock at it; they think becauſe it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ong before it be diſcovered, that it will never be. Alas, poor ſinners! <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll this while your ſecret ſins are ſet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the Light of Gods Countenance. O what folly is this, to think to hide <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hy ſin, and proſper? You ſinners,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:38361:33"/>that talk of your ſins being hid, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o you ever conſider theſe things? While your ſin is hid, your Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences will ſting you: O how will it flie in your Faces! Did not the guilt of <hi>Joſephs</hi> Brethren do ſo, after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Years it had been hid? When guilt ſhall have a Reſurrection by Conviction, and ſhall walk in your Conſciences, O how dreadful will this be! what a fearful <hi>Spectrum</hi> is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardoned guilt, when it walks in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> awakened Conſcience? Ah, ſinner doſt thou ever conſider this? What though thy ſin be hid, yet it will wal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in thy Conſcience? 2. Doſt tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conſider, though thy ſins be hid, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God hath all thy ſecret ſins in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Treaſures, (<hi>Deut.</hi> 32.34.) are th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not laid up in ſtore with him? A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they not ſealed up among his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures? Ah, ſinners, what fools a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you to think God hath forgott<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> them, until he hath forgiven them Though you have caſt them behin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:38361:33"/>your backs, yet God hath Treaſured <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem up: And, O, dreadful will this be when the Lord ſhall open theſe Treaſures, to bring them forth againſt you. 3. Sinners, did you ever conſider, there is a Court-Day coming, in which you muſt have all the Books opened, and it will be read out of theſe Books, what hath been hid for many Years; all ſinners In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictments are drawn out of theſe Books. <hi>And the Dead were Judged out of thoſe things which were written in the Books, according to their works,</hi> Rev. 20.11, 12. 4. Do you ever conſider, ſinners, that God often diſcovers that, which ſinners la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to hide moſt: If it be thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to hide it, God will make it his deſign to diſcover it. Ah, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, how ſad is it to carry on con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Deſigns to God? 5. Did you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ver conſider, that you have not more ways of ſinning, than God hath of diſcovering. Sometimes
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:38361:34"/>God makes uſe of Conſcience to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover ſin, ſometimes he makes u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of Providence to diſcover ſin, as in <hi>Jonahs</hi> caſe. The ſtorm is ſent to diſcover the guilty Perſon, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by Ordinances, ſometimes by ſuch as were Partners with you in your ſin. Ah, ſinners, put all theſe things together, and you will ſee hiding of your ſin is a poor Plea to make a mock at it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Sinners are led into the evil o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mocking at ſin, by ſin growing ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful and proſperous. When the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſee the path of the wicked to proſper O how are they hardned by it! <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.24. <hi>The proſperity of Fools ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> them.</hi> Such Fools are we to thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a proſperous Condition a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, but it hath been the undoing of many a poor Soul to all Eternity O how did the Church of the <hi>Jew</hi> (<hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.7, 8.) run from God after other Lovers, until God hedged u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> her way with Thorns, and mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:38361:34"/>
               <p>Wall to prevent her? And how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id the Prodigal, like a fooliſh Son <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat cauſeth ſhame, run from his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Houſe, (<hi>Luke</hi> 16.17.) until his Father ſent a Famine after him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd denied him Succour in his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acy; <hi>For he would gladly have fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed his belly with the Husks which the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> wine did eat, but no Man gave unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>im.</hi> Rubs in the ways of ſin are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eat Mercies; what mercy it is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave a Rub in the way to Hell, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing a ſinner to a ſtand, that ſtand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay bring him to a turn: Firſt, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ner comes to a ſtand of Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, before he comes to a turn of converſion. <hi>I conſidered my ways</hi> (ſays <hi>David</hi>) <hi>and turned my feet to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y Teſtimonies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Another thing that leads Fools <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> make a mock at ſin, is Gods defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g Puniſhment: when ſinners ſee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> eſcape the ſtrokes of Divine Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ance, then they begin to think <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> at ſin is but a ſport. Becauſe God
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:38361:35"/>kept ſilent, <hi>(viz.)</hi> did not preſently thunder upon them with the Tokens of his Wrath: What was the uſe they made of it? <hi>They thought God was like unto themſelves,</hi> Pſal. 50.21. Now they fall into <hi>Atheiſtical</hi> thoughts concerning God, and ſurely this will lead them to make a mock at ſin, if they once come to make a mock at God: Thus were they hardned, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom Sentence was not ſpeedily Executed. O how many poor fools have been hardned, and flattered by this, to the Gallows here, and to Hell hereafter.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Another thing that leads Fools to make a mock at ſin, is, they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have felt it a Burden upon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> back of their Conſciences: An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> poor Soul that hath felt it weigh, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dare ſay, is paſt making a mock a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it. <hi>David</hi> will tell you how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> weighed upon him; <hi>It went over h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Head as a Burden, yea, as too heav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a Burden to bear.</hi> It is the heavie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:38361:35"/>thing in the World, to ſuch as have felt the burden of it; and it is the bittereſt thing in the World, to ſuch as have taſted the bitterneſs of it. It is true, Afflictions are heavy burdens, and Temptations are heavy burdens; Doubts, and Objections, that preſs in upon many a Believers ſoul, are heavy burdens; but alas! theſe are all light things comparative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to the guilt of ſin. What a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den was ſin, upon the backs of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels? Did it not tumble them head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into Hell? What a burden was it upon our firſt Parents, did it not tumble them out of Paradiſe? O what a burden was it to our dear Lord, Jeſus Chriſt! Did not he cry out under it? Though they were not his own ſins, but our ſins which he took upon him. And could you mock at this, if ever you had felt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t? Ah what fools are poor ſinners! many Thouſands are ſunk into the Pit of Eternal Perdition, with the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:38361:36"/>weight and burden of their ſins, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the back of their Immortal ſouls.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Thing that leads ſinners to make a mock at ſin, is cuſtome in ſin. This is very hardning, we ſay it is a ſecond Nature.<note place="margin">Conſuetudo pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candi tollit ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum peccati.</note> Alas, when Souls have got a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of ſinning, then they begin to make a mock at it, being har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened in it. O how often doth the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of ſin, take away the feeling and conſcience of it. That is a great word in the Prophet, <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.23. <hi>Can the</hi> Ethiopian <hi>change his skin? Or the</hi> Leopard <hi>his ſpots? The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> may you do good, that are accuſtomed to do evil?</hi> And yet how ordinary is it, for theſe poor Fools to plead a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome for ſinning, which is ſo far from being a Plea, that it is an aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. I have, ſay Sinners, got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten a cuſtome of it, I cannot leave it. Tell a ſinner of his Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, of his Uncleanneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> O h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:38361:36"/>hath gotten a cuſtome of it: Is this any Plea, thou fooliſh ſinner? Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a Malefactor before a Judg of Aſſize, ſhould plead thus, My Lord, the Indictment is true, I confeſs the Fact; but I have gotten ſuch a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome to Steal, and play the Thief; or, I have gotten ſuch a cuſtome of it, to cut Purſes, that I cannot leave it, therefore I crave your Lordſhips favour. Would this pleading Mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate, or Aggravate the Offence, think you? And yet is not this the Caſe of Thouſands of ſinners? Some have Allegorized that paſſage of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> being dead four days, as though it ſet out a ſinner dead in his ſins and treſpaſſes; dead the firſt day <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y conceiving ſin, the ſecond day by conſenting to ſin, the third day by committing ſin, the fourth day by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſtome in ſin; ſo that a Sinner ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to ſin, is not only dead, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut buried in ſin, and a Grave-ſtone <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olled upon it, and now no ſenſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:38361:37"/>left in this ſinner, being dead in ſin, he becomes a mocker at ſin.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Another thing that leads fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh ones into mocking at ſin, is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it doth not appear to them at preſent in its proper colours, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to them in Diſguiſes, in Masks. Sinners do not look at ſin, in two Glaſſes, and ſo have not a right view and proſpect of it. (1.) The Glaſs of the Law, this will make ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to appear in its proper colours. <hi>Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> (ſays <hi>Paul</hi>) that it might appear ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it did not appear ſin before, it did not look like it ſelf before; it had a painted Face, but now it hath death in the Face of it, yea, Hell and Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in the Face of it. <hi>Sin revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and I died,</hi> Rom. 7.9, 10, 11, 12, 13. The Apparition of it, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſight of it kill'd him. O what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thing is ſin, that thou mockſt a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> poor ſinner! The ſight of it will ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a man. He had been looking upon his ſin in the Glaſs, of the Law, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:38361:37"/>Commandment. Alas! Do not the moſt of ſinners in the World, look upon ſin like a painted Lion, that cannot take a Man by the Throat. O, but the Law of God will let you ſee, it is a real Roaring Lion, and will tear you to pieces, if you get it not pardoned. (2.) There is the Glaſs of the Goſpel, to ſhew you ſin in its proper colours. The Goſpel lets you ſee, ſin is the Knife that cut the Throat of Gods <hi>Iſaac (viz.)</hi> the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. This was the Dagger that ſtab'd the Son of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the Heart. This was the Spear that let Water and Blood out of his ſide. The Nailes that faſtned his Sacred Hands to the Croſs. And if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hou hadſt ſuch a ſight of ſin, couldſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hou, nay, durſt thou, make a mock <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſin?</p>
               <p n="7">7. Another thing that leads Fools <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> make a mock at ſin, is, their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief of the ſevere Threatnings of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od againſt it. Though the Lord
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:38361:38"/>hath threatned it with Eternal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, with Deſtruction, yea, everlaſting Deſtruction from his Preſence, and the Glory of his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; to lie under Wrath to come, without the leaſt hopes of Mercy, to all Eternity. But alas! theſe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners are ſuch fools, that they put them far from them, and ſo make a mock at that they ſhould mourn o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Did they believe the ſoul that ſins ſhall die? Did they believe <hi>that the wages of ſin is death?</hi> Did they believe that the wayes of ſin do lead down unto death? Did they believe that Jeſus Chriſt will come in flaming fire, rendring Vengeance to them that know him not, and obey not the Goſpel? Could it be that they durſt make a mock at ſin? But alas! Do not all theſe ſevere Threatnings, ſeem to them like ſo many idle Tales; as things ſpoken they think meerly (<hi>in Terrorem</hi> and that God will never make the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:38361:38"/>good upon them. But what a dream, what a deluſion is this? God will as ſurely perform his Threatnings, as he will his Promiſes. Not one Threatning ſhall fall to the ground, no more than one Promiſe.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Another thing that leads Fools to make a mock at ſin, is this; A ſecret apprehenſion that they have taken up, that God will never call them to an account hereafter, for what ſin they run into now. O, if poor ſinners did but reckon of a day of Account, of ſtanding before a Judgment Seat, of being called be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Gods Bar; could they, durſt they make a mock at ſin? Did the Thief in the act conſider, I muſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for this before the Judg, would it not ſtrike him with dread and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, while he is about it? Would he then make a mock at it? What, at that which he muſt anſwer for? And ſinner, hath not God ſaid, we muſt all appear at his Judgment Seat?
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:38361:39"/>And that to give an account of all the deeds done in the Body, whether they be good or evil? And hath not he told us, after death we muſt come to Judgment? And that we muſt give an account for every idle word, at the great Audit-Day? Then ſurely, we muſt for every action, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.36. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.5. Is not Chriſt Judg of the Quick and the Dead, before whom we muſt all appear? And ſinner, is all this in Jeſt, can the Holy God thus dally with guilty ſinners? What is all this an idle ſtory? Is this only a Romance? Are theſe only big words? Come, come, poor ſinners, you will find every ſyllable of this to be true, and will you go on mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at that which you muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable for to an Impartial Judg? Will the Judgment Day be a mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing matter? Is the dreadful Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of God a jeſting Buſineſs? Then go on like Fools, and make a mock of ſin.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:38361:39"/>9. Thing that leads Fools to make a mock at ſin, is, a wretched Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit ſinners have taken up, that God will forget ſin, as faſt as they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it. Tuſh, ſay they, will God remember? <hi>He hath ſaid in his heart God hath forgotten, he hideth his face, he will never ſee it,</hi> Pſal. 10.11. And ſo poor deluded ſouls go on, making a mock at it. Ah poor ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner! what a madneſs is this in thee, to harbour ſuch a Conceit! God did foreſee ſuch a piece of Atheiſm as this in the hearts of the Sons of Men, therefore he hath laid us in with plentiful Texts of Scripture againſt it, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.34. <hi>Is not this laid up in ſtore with me, and ſealed among my Treaſures?</hi> God hath laid them up, to bring them out when occaſion ſerves. Therefore you read that in <hi>Job,</hi> Job 14.17. <hi>My tranſgreſſion is ſealed up in a bag, thou ſoweſt up mine iniquity.</hi> Some read it, <hi>Thou packeſt up mine iniquity.</hi> Others
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:38361:40"/>complicate them together, <hi>Lays one of them upon the top of another.</hi> Former ſins with preſent ſins, to make up the pack, and aggravate one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. When the great Aſſizes come, we read how ſinners muſt be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded againſt, out of the Books which are written, (ſays the Text, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.15.) O poor Sinners, will you, dare you, make a mock of that which God keeps a Remembrance of, which God Books down. Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, think what you will, your ſins are ſo far from being forgotten by God, that your iniquity is marked before the Lord, as he told them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.22. No, no, the Day is coming, God will reprove you, and ſet your ſins in order before you, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.20. An Alluſion to letters in a Book that are ſet in order, all in a row, before one. The Lord hath, Sinners, ſuch a Book where all your ſins are Recorded; and out of this Book you ſhall one day be
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:38361:40"/>forced to read all in their proper or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; you will then ſee God hath not forgotten any of them, no, not ſo much as the circumſtances of them, <hi>All is remembred.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. Another thing that leads Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to make a mock at ſin, is their ſtifling and ſtrangling their Convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of ſin, until they bring themſelves under obduracy of heart. Many ſinners at firſt ſinning, are arreſted with the Accuſations of their own guilty tormenting Conſciences, but then they run into one Diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or another, to ſwallow up and drown their convictions and troubles; as <hi>Cain</hi> did, when he went out from the preſence of God, and dwelt in the Land of <hi>Nod,</hi> and buildt a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.16. Which ſome think, was to divert the troubles of an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened guilty Conſcience: Many wounded Souls will run to their Pleaſures for a little eaſe, others to their Comforts, others to their Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings;
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:38361:41"/>and at laſt, their Convictions wear off, and then the Sinner comes to be hardned, and now he arrives at the height of ſin, even to make a mock of it. For uſually, Perſons who have been under ſome common work and troubles for Sin, and not being throughly wrought upon by them, become Mockers and Scoffers afterwards. O therefore, Sinners, look that your Convictions be through and through. O beg of God they may not be tranſient like a flaſh of Lightning in a Room, that makes it a little lighter for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, but leaves it dark when it is gone. Now, Sinners, you have heard the occaſions, that leads you into making a mock of Sin; Will you remember to pray againſt them, that it may not be thus with you, that you be not the Fools in the Text.</p>
               <p>Now to convince you, poor Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, that this is the greateſt Folly
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:38361:41"/>in the World, to make a mock at Sin.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Is it not Folly to make a mock at that, which you muſt certainly either mourn for here, or hereafter? As merry, poor Sinner, as thou art, thy mirth is but madneſs. <hi>I have ſaid to Laughter, thou art mad; and to Mirth, what doth it?</hi> Eccleſ. 2.2. It holds in this ſenſe, it lays a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for ſorrow, and bitter lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. (1.) Here, if God have a deſign of love upon thee, he will bring thee to mourn over that which thou haſt ſo often mockt at. Can you ever (ſinners) expect to be pardoned, if you have not repented? Doth he comfort any that do not mourn? <hi>Bleſſed are they that mourn, for they ſhall be comforted.</hi> Ah, Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, if thou didſt but remember in thy Jollity and Madneſs, when thou art making a mock of Sin, ere long thou muſt be made to mourn over it, and cry out of it, as a burden too
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:38361:42"/>heavy for thee to bear. Would not this check thee in thy careere of Madneſs and Folly? (2.) If thou mourn not over it here, it will be worſe, thou wilt be made to mourn over it hereafter, and then thou wilt mourn without hope. Now thou mayeſt have hope of pardon, there is hope concerning this thing, but this afterwards mourning, is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether hopeleſs; which makes me remember the ſad condition of that poor ſinner, <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.11, 12, 13, 14. <hi>And thou mourn at laſt when thy fleſh and thy body is conſumed, and ſay, How have I hated Inſtruction, and my heart deſpiſed Reproof? And have not obeyed the voice of my Teachers, nor enclined mine ear to them that inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted me. I was in all evil in the midſt of the Congregation and Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly.</hi> Whether we took it of mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing here in old Age, (as ſome) or of mourning in Hell (as others) yet it holds true: O what a mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:38361:42"/>will this be! (Some read it <hi>Quoniam</hi>) Becauſe I have hated In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. (Others read it <hi>Cur</hi>) Why have I hated Inſtruction: As being a Confeſſion, he had no Cauſe, no Reaſon, to do ſo. We read it <hi>(Quomodo)</hi> How have I hated In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction? As being an acquitting Gods Juſtice in his puniſhment. O, how have I hated Inſtruction, and it is but juſt with God, I now ſhould be thus dealt withal; God is Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in all this, that is come upon me. And is not this folly? great folly to lay the foundation of ſuch mourning, and ſuch bitter mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Is not this Folly, to mock at that which the Righteous God hates with a perfect hatred, yea, and will be revenged of? Did poor Sinners ſee, God hated ſin, would they make a mock at it? That you make a matter of Mockery of, God makes a matter of hatred of. As in that caſe
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:38361:43"/>of Idolatry, ſo in this, he ſays, <hi>Do not the abominable thing my ſoul hates,</hi> Jer. 44.4. And it is ſaid of Chriſt, <hi>He loves Righteouſneſs, and hates Iniquity,</hi> Heb. 1.9. And do you think this is a mocking buſineſs, Sirs? Nay, God's hatred boyls up into Revenge: <hi>Shall not my ſoul be avenged on ſuch a Nation as this?</hi> And is it not a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the Everliving God? Who hath ſaid, <hi>Vengeance is his, and he will repay.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, God will either be avenged of Sin here, or hereafter. He often takes Vengeance of it here, and ſhall Sinners make a mock at Gods Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? How many thouſands hath. God taken Vengeance of in this Life? How hath Gods Righteous Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments often taken hold of this wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Perſon, or that wicked Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly?</p>
               <p>Secondly, Hereafter we read o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt coming <hi>in flaming Fire,</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:38361:43"/>2 Theſ. 1.8. to take vengeance on poor Sinners that know him not, nor have obeyed his Goſpel. And do not we read of the Vengeance of Eternal Fire? (<hi>Jude, ver.</hi> 7.) And is this a mocking matter with you? Will there be any Laughter, any Mocking, any Drollery in Hell? Now, you Sinners make a meer piece of Drollery about Sin, but ſtay when you come under a ſentence of Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, that will be no Drollery with you.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Is not that Folly, yea, great Folly, to make a mock at that which grieves God? We would not grieve the deareſt Friend, thy dear Father, thy dear Husband, thy dear Wife, would you willingly grieve them? And, O what folly is this to grieve God! to grieve that God that thou daily liveſt upon, that is thy deareſt Friend in the World? Do you know what you do Sinners, when you grieve God?</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:38361:44"/>
               <p>Firſt, What, grieve that God tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you depend upon for your lives, for the lives of your Souls, for the lives of your Bodies, who can both kill Body and Soul: He that is Lord of your Lives, and can ſeal a Leaſe of Ejectment when he will; Turn you out of your Clay Cottages at his pleaſure.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Is it not folly to grieve him, that can call you to an account when he will? You muſt be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to him for your grieving of him, at his own time and pleaſure.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Is it not a folly to grieve him that we cannot contend with? Is there any ſtanding out with God? Did ever any <hi>harden himſelf againſt the Lord and proſper?</hi> Job 9.4. Did you never, Sinners, read that word ſeriouſly over? <hi>Can your hearts en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, or your hands be made ſtrong in that day that I ſhall deal with you?</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.14. You may, it may be, endure through the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:38361:44"/>hardneſs of your hearts, the day that Gods Servants deal with you: But, Oh Sinner, God's day of deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with thee, will be another kind of Day!</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Is it not folly to grieve him, that hath done you ſo many kindneſſes? Is not this great Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, and is not this Folly? O fooliſh People, and unwiſe, will you thus requite the Lord?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Is not this Folly to mock at that which coſt Jeſus Chriſt his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Blood? What died the Lord Jeſus Chriſt for? Was it not the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins? <hi>Without ſhedding of blood</hi> (ſays the Apoſtle) <hi>there is no Remiſſion.</hi> Heb. 1.3. <hi>When Chriſt had purged by himſelf our ſins, he ſate down at the right Hand of the Majeſty on high.</hi> Ah, poor ſinners, do not you tread the Blood of Chriſt under foot, and account it an unclean thing, while you make a mock at ſin? O hard hearted wretches, can you
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:38361:45"/>make a mock at that which let out the Heart Blood of Chriſt! Can you make that a matter of Laughter, which made the Lord Jeſus ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, even unto death? Can you mock at the Gall and Vinegar that thoſe cruel <hi>Jews,</hi> that Crucified our Lord, gave him to drink? Would you have Laughed to have ſeen him hang upon the Croſs? You all, that make a mock at ſin, do as much as if you Laught at him when he went to Execution: And is it not, Sinners, to Crucifie him again, and to put him to open ſhame?</p>
               <p n="5">5. Is it not a Folly to mock at that which brought the Curſe into the World; until Sin entred into the World, there was no ſuch thing as the Curſe known; and to mock at ſin, is to mock at the Curſe. O, what madneſs is this! To mock at that which ſhortly you muſt feel the effects of! which conſiſts in two things:</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:38361:45"/>
               <p>Firſt, Death Temporal. <hi>In the day thou eateſt thereof, thou ſhalt ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly die.</hi> Would you know how Death, that King of Terrours, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the World? and hath ſuch an univerſal and uncontrollable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency in the World? (The Apoſtle anſwers it) <hi>Death entred into the World by ſin,</hi> Rom. 5.12. Ah, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, will you make a mock at Death? Is dying a jeſting matter with you? Will you mock when this grim Serjeant ſhall Arreſt you? Will not then your mocking be turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into mourning? Doth the guilty condemned Malefactor, when ready to be turned off the Ladder, uſe to die mocking at the Executioner? I believe, when you lie a dying, you will tell another ſtory.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The Curſe that ſin hath brought, conſiſts in eternal Death, called the ſecond Death. The firſt Death, that conſiſts of ſeparation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Soul and Body; but the ſecond
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:38361:46"/>Death, that conſiſts in a ſeperation betwixt the Soul and God; it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Everlaſting deſtruction from the preſence of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Is it not a Folly to make a mock at that which hath made many a poor Soul go groaning under the weight and burden of it, many a Day, yea, many a Year? Poor ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, you may ſport at it for a while, but if the Lord once make you feel the Load of it, and lay upon you the Senſe of it, then your Note will be changed. What was it that made <hi>David</hi> cry out, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.4, 5, 6, 7. <hi>My Wounds ſtink, and are corrupt.</hi> And at another time, <hi>My Sores run day and night, and ceaſeth not. I am troubled, I am bowed down greatly, I go mourning all the day long. I have roared by reaſon of the diſquietneſs of my heart.</hi> What was the matter? What occaſioned this tumult in the Soul of poor <hi>David?</hi> He tells us, <hi>For mine in quities are gone over mine
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:38361:46"/>head as a burden, as too heavy a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den for me to bear,</hi> &amp;c. And, poor Sinner, wilt thou mock at that, which other gracious Souls have ſo ſadly mourned over? Poor penitent Souls, are called <hi>weary and heavy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Souls.</hi> And ſhall it be to you a jeſting, mocking buſineſs?</p>
               <p n="7">7. Is it not a great Folly to mock at that, which Satan is ſo earneſtly ſolicitous to draw Souls into? It is the great deſign of Satan, to draw Souls into Sin and Guilt. It is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>The work of the Devil.</hi> O how induſtrious is he in tempting! O how diligent is he, in laying ſnares for poor Sinners! And ſhall Sinners mock at Satans ſnares? Are not Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners his Vaſſals and Captives? And is this a mocking matter to be tied to his Chariot Wheels? To be lead in triumph by this devourer and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer of Souls? Would you make a mock at a company of poor Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, that are taken by the <hi>Turks?</hi>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:38361:47"/>and there put into the Galleys, or cruelly beaten and abuſed, by their hard hearted <hi>Patroons?</hi> And is not this the caſe. Ah, poor Soul! thou art Captive to Satan for all thy mocking: Thou art in a worſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition than any Galley-Slave in the World, though thou art not ſenſible of it.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Is it any mocking matter to mock at that, which degraded An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Men? How came Angels to be degraded from that Dignity and Honour, in which they were Created? We read an Anſwer to the Queſtion, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4. <hi>God ſpared not Angels that ſinned, but caſt them down to Hell, and delivered them into Chains of darkneſs, to be reſerved un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Judgment.</hi> Theſe Angels were glorious Courtiers once, though condemned Priſoners now: What was then the matter for which they were thus ſeverely dealt with? They rebelled againſt God, and ſo were
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:38361:47"/>degraded from their firſt Station. <hi>Jude</hi> tells us, <hi>They kept not their firſt Station, their firſt Eſtate,</hi> Jude, ver. 6. Secondly, Sin degraded Man, and ſhall we mock at that which degra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded us from that excellent State in which we were Created? <hi>Man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Honour abideth not, he is like the Beaſt that periſheth,</hi> Pſal. 49.12. Or, <hi>Adam ledged not in Honour, no, not one night,</hi> as the <hi>Hebrew</hi> reads it. And the Septuagint, <hi>He underſtood not.</hi> He underſtood not the Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of that Eſtate in which he was Created, and ſo was degraded. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this a mocking matter, Sinners? To be degraded and ſtript of that glorious Robe of Original Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, with which he was in his Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive State clothed? To be rob'd of Communion with God, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to God, in which conſiſted his Excellency, and to be degraded of this Glory, O, ſinners, is this a mocking matter? Put all theſe
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:38361:48"/>Particulars together, and weigh them in the Ballance of the Sanctuary, and lay them to your hearts, and then ask your Souls this Queſtion: Ah, my Soul, is ſin a mocking, jeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Buſineſs? Argue them over with thy Soul, and ſee, if thou canſt bring thy ſelf to a ſober ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in this Debate, and make a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of thy Folly, in thinking ſin to be a mocking matter.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Application.</head>
                  <p>Is it ſuch egregious Folly to make a mock at ſin? Then it informs us of the madneſs of all impenitent, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, merry Sinners. There are a company of Jovial Sinners, in this mad Age of this World, that are running head-long to their eternal Ruine laughing, that ſwim down merrily the ſtream of the ſins of the preſent day, to that Lake that burns
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:38361:48"/>with Fire and Brimſtone; and the miſery of it, there is no ſtopping them, becauſe they are inſenſible whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they are going. They ſay, there is a Serpent, that when Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers are bit with it, they die Laughing: And is not this Sin, this Serpent? Do not many die eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally Laughing? Go to the Pit of eternal Perdition, as ſome ranting condemned Malefactors do to Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution. But alas, poor Sinner, for all thy Laughing, and Mirth, and Mocking at ſin now, ere long, thy Note will be altered, when thou ſhalt be ſtated irrecoverably; <hi>Where there is nothing but weeping, and wail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and gnaſhing of Teeth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That ſuch Merry Sinners may be reduced a little to their Reaſons and right Minds, let me ask them a few Queſtions; and beg of them, as they love their Souls, that they would put them home to their own
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:38361:49"/>Souls and Conſciences, before they go hence, and be no more ſeen.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Doſt thou know, O poor fooliſh Sinner, whither thou art go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? Didſt thou never ask thy heart this Queſtion, whither thy ſin, and mocking at ſin, will lead thee at laſt? Wilt thou meet with thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Companion in another World, to rejoyce together, to ſport toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as you have done upon Earth? Is there any ſuch Trade driven on in Hell? Are there any Mockers at ſin there? Is there any Mirth and Jol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity there? Doth not the infallible Oracle of the Word of God tell us, there is weeping, and gnaſhing of Teeth? Is there one word of Laughing? What, Sinner, never come thus cloſe with thy own Soul, before thou lie on a Death-bed? Come, Sinner, be perſwaded to put the Queſtion home, it may ſo prove, thou mayſt bleſs God for it, to all Eternity.</p>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:38361:49"/>
                  <p>Secondly, Doſt thou remember, Sinner, what thou art doing while ſinning? Art thou not provoking a Great and Good God? What art thou doing, O my Soul! treaſuring up Wrath againſt the day of Wrath? Wounding thy precious ſoul, <hi>and a wounded ſpirit who can bear?</hi> Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry time thou ſinneſt againſt God, art thou not carrying Fewel to the Eternal Flames, to torment thy own ſoul? Doth not every one that ſins againſt God, wrong his own ſoul? And what is this, a mocking mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter?</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Doſt thou remember, Sinner, what a little time thou haſt to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin in, thou art ſo mad upon? Theſe are but for a ſeaſon, and then thou wilt ſay with him, O, for how ſhort a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, have I loſt a Kingdom! Will not thou ere long, be ſaying, O, for how ſhort a pleaſure, have I loſt a precious, Immortal Soul, and an
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:38361:50"/>everlaſting Kingdom? Methinks, Sinners, the ſhortneſs of your time, ſhould make you think of ſomething elſe, than making a mock at ſin. O, that Sinners would be perſwaded to argue in the midſt of their ſinful mirth and madneſs. O, but will this laſt always?</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, Doſt thou remember wherefore thou cameſt in the World? Doſt thou never ask thy own Heart the Errand thou cameſt on hither? Was it to ſin, or make a mock of ſin? Was it to diſhonour that God, that gave thee Life and Being? Did God give thee an Immortal Soul ſo to degrade thy ſelf, as to mock at ſin? Did God ſend thee into the World, to lift up the heel againſt him, that had Bowels and pity in his Heart towards thee? Was it to laugh at him, who mourns for thee? To ſpit in the Face of thy dear Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, who hath wept over thee, as he did over <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> (as I may ſay)?</p>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:38361:50"/>
                  <p>Fifthly, Doſt thou remember thou muſt anſwer for thy bold preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Is not this bold preſumption to make a mock at ſin? Didſt thou ever ſee a condemned Malefactor laugh in the face of an angry Judg? And yet what is this leſs, poor Sinner, that thou doeſt, when thou makeſt a mock at ſin?</p>
                  <p>Sixthly, Doſt thou ever remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Day is faſt approaching, that thou wilt cry to the Mountains, and to the Rocks, <hi>cover us from the Wrath of the Lamb, that ſits upon the Throne?</hi> O what a change of thy Tune is here, poor ſinner! now thou canſt not make a mock at ſin! O now thou feeleſt the burden of ſin intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and inſupportable! O, how will ſuch Souls cry out of it!</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The ſecond <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
                  <p>Is it ſo, that 'tis ſo great a folly to make a mock at ſin? O then, be cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:38361:51"/>(poor ſinners) how you glory in that, which is your ſhame, and run on in that, which will be your ruine! If you glory in that which is your ſhame, (obſerve) it is ſaid of ſuch, <hi>Their end is deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> Phil. 3.19. You have heard, what a folly it is to mock at that, which will certainly cauſe your mourning another day? May it not be ſaid to ſuch, <hi>Woe be to them that laugh, for they ſhall mourn.</hi> You will find, ſinners, it is no laughing buſineſs one day: Is it not a folly to make a mock at that, the Righteous God hates with a perfect hatred? Reflect upon the former particulars, and will you not take heed for all theſe warnings, how you go on in theſe ſinful Courſes? Shall all this be ſaid unto you in vain, poor Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners? Do you think, God, and Chriſt, the Spirit, Scriptures, Miniſters and Conſcience are all in Jeſt, while they tell you the danger of making a
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:38361:51"/>mock at ſin? Can you rationally think, that God hath ſaid, what he hath ſaid againſt ſin only [in <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rorem:</hi>] No, Sinners, you ſhall all know, that ſin is ſuch a two edged Weapon, that there is no jeſting with it.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, be cautioned againſt making a mock at ſin: This is the higheſt degree, that Sinners arrive at in this Life, it is the height of ſin; it is bad enough to ſin, but it is worſe to make a mock of it. Sin is folly, but to make a mock at ſin, is the height of folly and madneſs: Would not you think him a Mad-man, that ſhould wound and gaſh his fleſh, and all this while laugh at himſelf for ſo doing, and becauſe he doth not feel it at preſent, conclude that he ſhall never feel it afterwards, would not every one ſay, he was fit for <hi>Bedlam?</hi> And is not this the caſe of Sinners, that make a mock at ſin? They are like him (you read of, <hi>Mar.</hi> 5.5.) that
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:38361:52"/>was among the Tombs and Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and cut himſelf with ſtones. So ſinners are cruelly gaſhing their own ſouls, and yet all this while like a company of condemned Priſoners, Singing and Ranting before their Execution. Would you not think him a Mad-man indeed, that ſhould laugh in the face of the Judg, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a Sentence of Law upon him, to go from the Bar to the Gibbet? This is ſuch an high degree of ſin, that Scorners are ſaid to be in the higheſt Form in Satan's ſchool, and that he is a bleſſed Man, that is not one with them in this Form. <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is the Man that walketh not in the councel of the ungodly.</hi> Here is one degree, one form in this School. <hi>Nor ſtandeth in the way of ſinners:</hi> Here is another Form of Sinners, and this is ſtill an higher Form. <hi>Nor fitteth in the ſeat of the ſcornful,</hi> Pſal. 1.1. This is the higheſt Form in in all the Devil's School. This is to
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:38361:52"/>take the<note n="*" place="margin">The Septu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agint reads it.</note> 
                     <hi>Chair,</hi> it is called the Chair, or Seat of Peſtilence. To note the height, and hainouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it. Other Sins are like or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Diſeaſes, but this is the Plague, this is the Peſtilence, this is the higheſt Infection, the higheſt Malignity of Sin: Such Sinners have taken their Degree, they are Maſters of this Black Art, and are in the Chair. For the <hi>Hebrew [Moſhab,]</hi> is uſed for a Chair. And will not you be cautioned, poor Sinners, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch a piece of Sin, which is the higheſt degree of Folly and Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?</p>
                  <p>Secondly, O take heed, poor Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, of making a mock at ſin! This degree of ſin arrived at, very rarely are poor ſinners converted from; (I do not ſay) but the Lord hath had Mercy of ſome gone thus far. But ſuch Inſtances are very rare, very ſeldom heard of. When
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:38361:53"/>a ſinner is gotten into this Seat, or Chair, it is a very hard thing to raiſe him. They frequenly die upon this Seat; Satan puts forth all his power, to hold his own; he lulls them aſleep in this Chair; it is the Sinners ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Chair, and their ſleep uſually is unto death. Thoſe die of a Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Lethergy, they are not in an ordinary way recovered, if at any time they be. Some of Satans ſnares are more eaſily broken, but this holds many, until they be found dead in it: The Bands of mockers are uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally made ſtrong. O then, poor Sinners; will not you take heed of coming under ſuch Bands?</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, O take heed of being mockers at ſin! many times ſuch have had ſtrange teſtimonies born a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. O, how often hath God reached forth his hand againſt ſuch, in a very eminent manner! He hath not let this ſin, of all others, go unpuniſhed. When Men come
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:38361:53"/>to glory in their ſhame, then God makes their end deſtruction: <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are prepared for ſinners, and ſtripes for the backs of fools,</hi> Prov. 19.29. They muſt be ſure great Judgments, that are prepared Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; yea, prepared Judgments by the great God. It ſpeaks the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Judgment, as preparing Mercy ſpeaks the greatneſs of his Mercy: <hi>How great are thoſe things</hi> (ſays the Apoſtle) <hi>God hath prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for them, that love him.</hi> They are Judgments too; not one Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but variety of Judgments: Little do ſuch ſinners know, what they expoſe themſelves unto: <hi>When the ſcorners are puniſhed, the ſimple is made wiſe,</hi> Prov. 21.11. It ſeems the Puniſhments are ſo great, that they become teaching Examples un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to others. <hi>They that mocked the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of the Lord, did not wrath come upon them, and that without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy?</hi> 2 Chron. 36.16, I might
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:38361:54"/>give you Inſtances out of Hiſtory, but I refer the Reader to Doctor <hi>Beard's Theatre of Gods Judgments.</hi> To Mr. <hi>Fox</hi>'s Book of Martyrs, and to Mr. <hi>Clerks Examples,</hi> leaſt this Piece ſhould ſwell too bulky for the Readers Purſe.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, Take heed of mocking at ſin, in this doing, you mock at God himſelf, and will God be thus mocked? Mocking at ſin, is virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally mocking at God. 1. Do not you in thus doing, mock at the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of God? Who many times makes Examples of ſuch Perſons: If he be a Juſt God, and will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Proud and the Evil doers, will you mock at ſin, that God in his Juſtice is engaged ſooner or later to puniſh? Is not he the Judg of all the Earth, and will not he do right? He that makes a mock at Stealing, and Murder, and Robbery, doth not he make a mock of the Judg up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Bench, that ſits to paſs Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:38361:54"/>upon theſe Crimes? And will a Judg upon the Bench bear it, to be mocked by the Priſoner at the Bar? O, ſinners, what do you do when you laugh at the Juſtice of God, which ere long, muſt paſs a final and an irreverſible Sentence upon your immortal ſouls! 2. To mock at ſin is to mock at the Holineſs of God. Is God an Holy God, and cannot look upon Iniquity? Is God ſo Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a God, that without Holineſs, no Man ſhall ever ſee him? Is God ſo Holy a God, as he is Glorious in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs? Is God ſo Holy a God, as he cannot be approached unto but out of the hand of a Mediator? Is God ſo Holy a God, as he could not bear the ſin of the fallen Angels (though thought to be) only ſin in thought? Is God ſo Holy a God, as to caſt <hi>Adam</hi> out of Paradiſe, upon his Fall? Is God ſo Holy a God, as he will not let ſin go unpuniſhed, in the deareſt of his Children? And will
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:38361:55"/>you not take heed how you mock at ſin, leſt you mock at the Holineſs of God? If God was not an Holy God, then you might mock on, but God being thus Holy, look you to it, poor ſinners. 3. While you make a mock at ſin, you mock at God's Threatnings, hath not the Lord dreadfully threatned ſin? What ſtand all his Threatnings upon Record for? What hath God told Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Wrath to come for? Is all this falſe Fire? Are all Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations in vain againſt ſin? Is there any thing in all the Word threatned with Judgments here, and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments hereafter, like ſin? Is not the wages of ſin death? Hath not God that will make it good, ſaid, <hi>The ſoul that ſins ſhall die?</hi> And ſhall not his Word of threatning, as ſure be made good upon Impenitent Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, as his Word of Promiſe ſhall be made good to Penitent Believers? You forget, Sinners, that ſin which
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:38361:55"/>you mock at, is the Butt that all the Arrows of Gods Threatnings are le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled at? Could you run on in Sin, but that you ſin off your ſouls, the ſenſe of Gods Threatnings againſt Sin? Should not you ſay, Sure there is ſomething in it, ſomething more than ordinary in it, that Sin ſhould be thus threatned by God? 4. Do not you make a mock at the Patience of God, while you make a mock at Sin? Do not you ſay with thoſe Mockers, and Scoffers, that <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks of, <hi>Where is the Promiſe of his coming?</hi> So many, that ſee for the preſent, that God doth not puniſh Sin, that Sentence is not ſpeedily executed; therefore their hearts are hardned, and they go on mocking at Sin. They ſee not that God is a Word, and a Blow, ſo quick as Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers make him to be; but the Lord keeps ſilence, and ſo they run on ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a mock at Sin. O, but poor Sinners know, the longer the Blow
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:38361:56"/>is fetching, the heavier it falls! Abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Patience, turns to Incenſed Wrath. If he have long refrained himſelf, and held his peace, when he crys, <hi>He will then cry like a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in Travel, and devour all at once,</hi> Iſa. 42.14. Poor Sinner, though God hath long kept Silence, yet he will not always keep Silence; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, poor Soul, look to it, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, remember thy Blow is coming, though it hath been kept off a great while. 5. While thou makeſt a mock at Sin, thou mockſt at the Power of God, as though God's Power could not reach thee, while thou art mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king at ſin. As though Gods Arm was ſhortned, that he could not ſtrike thee dead in the very Fact, when thou art making a mock at ſin. Have not many been ſo? How ſoon were thoſe forty two Children deſtroyed by the She-Bears that came out of the Wood, while they made a mock of the Servant of God, in ſaying to
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:38361:56"/>him, <hi>Go up thou Bald-head, go up thou Bald-head,</hi> 2 Kings 2.23, 24. Could not God as ſpeedily reach thee by his Power if he pleaſed, while thou art making a mock at ſin? 6. While thou mockeſt at ſin, doſt thou not make a mock of the Word of God, that hath ſo and ſo deſcribed ſin in its proper Colours; that is the only true Glaſs to repreſent the ugly Face of Sin in? do not you contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict all the Scriptures have ſaid of Sin, when you make a mock of it? Is Sin ſuch an evil as the Word ſays it is? What, and you make a mock of it? Is ſin ſo diſhonourable to God, that it pollutes his Name? Is ſin ſo defiling to precious Souls, that it pollutes them? Is it ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, that it will without ſincere Repentance, certainly Damn them? Hath not the Word told you, it grieves the Spirit of God, it wounds your own Conſciences, it kindles the Fire of Gods diſpleaſure againſt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:38361:57"/>Churches, and Cities, and Families, and particular Perſons? and is all this a mocking matter? And hath the Word of the Lord ſaid all this of it, and much more, in Jeſt? And will God bear his Word to be mockt at? Would not any King be angry, to have his Royal Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion laught at, and made a mocking Buſineſs of? 7. While you make a mock at ſin, do not you make a mock of the Meſſengers of God, the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of God? They are ſent to you from God, to lay open to you the danger of ſin, of continuing in ſin, of mocking at ſin; our Buſineſs is to Decry ſin, and Preach down ſin: <hi>Cry aloud, and ſpare not</hi> (is our Commiſſion) <hi>ſhew my People their Transgreſſions, and the Houſe of</hi> Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob <hi>their ſins,</hi> Iſa. 58.1. It is our Work to turn Men from their ſins, and while you make a mock at ſin, you do but make a mock of us and our Meſſage. Is it no ſin to mock at
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:38361:57"/>them which mourn over you? While they are weeping over you, you are mocking them? But, remember, <hi>While you deſpiſe them, you deſpiſe him that ſent them,</hi> Luke 10.16. You mock their Maſter. Laſtly, Take heed how you make a mock of Sin, for in this you do but make a mock of Chriſt the Son of God. Ah, Sinners, Sinners, how do you, with thoſe <hi>Jews,</hi> deride Chriſt. <hi>Luke</hi> 16.14. <hi>They derided him.</hi> The Word is <hi>[Blew their Noſes at him.]</hi> The higheſt Act of Scorn and Contempt imaginable. You cannot mock at Sin, but you muſt mock at Chriſt; this is to Crucifie the Son of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh; this is to put him to open ſhame; this is to account the Blood of Chriſt which was ſhed for Sin, an unclean thing; this is to make a mock at the Sufferings of our dear Lord Jeſus. What did he Die for? Was it not to Purge away Sin? Was it not to take away Sin? <hi>Behold the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:38361:58"/>Lamb of God, who takes away the ſins of the World.</hi> Do not we expect Redemption, and Remiſſion of ſin through his Blood? What, and make a mock of ſin? This is to ſpit in the Face of a Dying Jeſus, of a Satisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt. Now, Sinner, hear the Call of God, and ask thy own heart, if it be not high time to be wiſe for Salvation. Ah, poor ſoul! haſt thou not plaid the Fool too long in run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning on in ſin, in making a mock at ſin. Now, hear the Lord, ſaying, <hi>O ye ſimple, underſtand Wiſdom; and ye Fools, be of an underſtanding heart,</hi> Prov. 8.5. <hi>Forſake the Fooliſh and live, go in the Way of underſtanding. The fear of the Lord is the beginning of Wiſdom, and the knowledg of the Holy is underſtanding,</hi> Prov. 9.6, 10.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:38361:58"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
